A Guide to the Sidney B. Jeffreys Papers, 1927-1985
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Sidney B. Jeffreys Papers, 1927-1985
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Jeffreys, Sidney B. (Sidney Bryan), 1909-1986
Ms1986-007
1.0 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sidney B. Jeffreys Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1986.
Biographical / Historical
Sidney Bryan Jeffreys, a 1931 graduate of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech) and the founder of Jeffreys Engineering and Equipment Company (Jeeco), was born in Chase City, Virginia in 1909. After graduating from the Blackstone Military Academy (Nottoway County, Virginia), Jeffreys attended Virginia Polytechnic Instittue. He graduated with a bachelor's degree in industrial engineering in 1931, then obtained a master's degree in business and engineering administration from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology the following year. In the meantime, he had married Angie Eliza Turner in 1931, and the couple would have two children. (Following Angie Jeffreys' 1972 death, he would marry Gwendolyn Goodson Powell.)
Jeffreys began his career at the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce in 1933, working with the membership and serving as a liaison. The following year, he went to work in production engineering sales and service for Wright Aeronautical Corporation. In 1938, he joined Jeffreys Lumber Company of Raleigh, North Carolina, a family-run lumber manufacturing business, as secretary, general manager, and director. During (and after) these years, he also served as secretary and director of Jeffreys-Spaulding Manufacturing of Chase City. (The company merged with Georgia Pacific in 1965). Finally, in 1946, Jeffreys founded Jeffreys Engineering and Equipment Company (Jeeco) in Raleigh. Two years later, he moved the company to Greensboro, North Carolina. Jeffreys sold controlling interest in the corporation and retired in 1976.
As an alumnus of Virginia Tech, Jeffreys maintained an active relationship with his alma mater. He was a member of the Hokie Club, the Founders Century Club, and the Committee of 100. He served as permanent secretary and treasurer of the Class of 1931, served on the V.P.I. Educational Foundation, and initiated the fund for a named professorship for the Industrial Engineering and Operations Research Department. In 1981, he was honored as College of Engineering Distinguised Alumnus.
In addition to these activities, Jeffreys participated in a number of civic and professional organizations.
Sidney B. Jeffreys died on February 6, 1986.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the Virgina Tech-related papers of Sidney B. Jeffreys, a 1931 graduate of the university who, as an alumnus, played an active role in promoting and developing the university. The collection contains papers relating both to Jeffreys' years as a student and as an alumnus. Included are coursework, extracurricular ephemera, correspondence, reports, and printed materials. Among the correspondence in the alumnus series papers are letters from a number of university and alumni association officials, including H. B. "Puss" Redd, Paul Deering, Paul Torgersen, T. Marshall Hahn, and William E. Lavery.
Arrangement
The Sidney B. Jeffreys Papers are arranged in two series:
Series I. Student Papers, 1927-1931. This series contains papers arising from Jeffreys' academic and extracurricular activities while a student at Virginia Tech. Included is a an account--in diary form, but apparently written at the end of the academic year--chronicling Jeffreys' experiences as a freshman cadet. The series also includes instructions for the conduct of cadet parades and various pieces of memorabilia, including dance cards, invitations, menus, programs, class schedules, and other ephemera. Jeffreys' coursework is represented in drafting assignments, class notes, and graded papers.
Series II. Alumnus Papers, 1933-1985. The materials in this series reflect Jeffreys' active, ongoing interest in his alma mater. The series includes correspondence with officers of the alumni assocation and various university officials. Also included is correspondence between the school and Jeffreys company, Jeeco, regarding purchases as well as efforts to place recent Virginia Tech graduates in Jeeco company positions. The series includes files devoted to campus-related organizations to which Jeffreys belonged, including Alpha Pi Mu, Pi Kappa Alpha, and the Committee of 100. Much of the material relates to Jeffreys' support of the school, both as a financial donor and as a booster. Thus, the papers contain reports on alumni fundraising efforts, on Jeffreys' many visits to campus, his ongoing development work with the Engineering Department, and his service in representing the university in presidential inaugurations at Guilford College and Salem Academy and College. A few files at the end of the series relate more personally to Jeffreys and include printed materials and correspondence about his interest in the Eli Whitney musket; copies of Virginia Tech printed materials in which he is mentioned; and a few pieces of personal correspondence, much of which is from Lorana T. Moomaw and James G. Maley.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection to be added to the Rare Book Collection:
Students' Handbook of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1927/1928, 1928/1929, 1929/1930, 1930/1931
The Virginia Tech (extra edition), Nov. 10, 1928
"Land-Grant Centennial: VPI's 90th Year," ca. 1961
"Unity, Dedication, Precision: the World Famed Virginia Tech Regimental Band," [1963?]
Basketball program: Duke vs Virginia Tech, Dec. 1, 1967
Basketball program: Duke vs Virginia Tech, Nov. 30, 1968
"Virginia Tech 1971-1972 Calendar," 1971
"An Introduction to Virginia Tech," 1971
Epsilog: the Alumni Newsletter of the Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity, Epsilon Chapter Fall 1978, Spring/Summer 1978, Spring 1983, Summer 1983, Fall 1984, Winter 1984
"A Statement of Need: The College of Engineering, Virginia Tech," ca. 1982
The following items were removed from the collection to be added to the Historical Map Collection:
"A Guide to the Virginia Tech Campus," ca. 1963
"Virginia Tech Campus Guide," ca. 1971
"Virginia Tech Campus Guide," 1980
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Alumni Association
Contents List
- Series I: Student Papers, 1927-1931
  - Diary, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cadet parade manual, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dance cards, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Invitations, menus, and programs, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs and ephemera, 1927-1931, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class notes and graded papers, 1926-1931, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Freshman engineering drawings, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sophomore engineering drawings, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Engineering problems drawings, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Materials of Engineering reports, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Alumnus Papers, 1933-1985
  - Class of 1931 treasurer, 1933-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jeeco / Virginia Tech correspondence, 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Association correspondence and publications, 1948-1982, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association - Piedmont North Carolina Chapter, 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alpha Pi Mu, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pi Kappa Alpha, 1972-1984, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee of 100, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fundraising, 1955-1985, n,.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Campus events, 1965-1985, n.d., [2 folders] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - College of Engineering, 1949-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Industrial Engineering and Operations Research, 1963-1984, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Learning: To Approach the Twenty-first Century" - correspondence and background materials, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - College presidential inaugurations, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Virginia Tech correspondence, 1964-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Eli Whitney musket - correspondence and printed material, 1971-1973, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jeffreys in Virginia Tech publications, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Personal correspondence, 1953-1985, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)